# Michael W. Kearney, Ph.D.

Data Scientist NLP | AI | ML

mike.wayne.kearney@gmail.com

(816) 447-8650



### **Professional Summary**

Internationally recognized expert in Data Science, Natural Language, and Artificial Intelligence with over ten years of professional experience, strong theoretical and quantitative backgrounds, and a knack for finding and implementing innovative solutions to complex problems.

## **Professional Experience**

Al Consultant Aware (client) Michael Kearney Al Consulting LLC 2023

- Delivered recommendations on use and development of generative AI and large language models
- Described strengths and limitations in data sources and models and estimated project timelines
- Drafted plans to implement/monitor human-in-the-loop AI labeling and offer multi-tier API access

# Senior Data Scientist Language/Labs Aware 2021-2023

- Refactored, optimized, and implemented best practices for large language models
- Enabled multilingual training and converted pipelines from Airflow to Sagemaker Pipelines
- Proposed and built information quality model to supercharge ML and generative Al
- Curated external dataset containing 500 million heuristically labeled social messages
- Created internal packaging for external data collection, data visualization, and sampling
- Owned, improved, and expanded (to non-English) featured NLP models-sentiment & toxic speech
- Automated model reports on inputs, parameters, and metrics (precision, recall, f1, accuracy)
- Used SQL and Athena to efficiently query customer data in DynamoDB, Athena, and Redshift
- Frequently worked with datalakes, Apache Arrow columnar format, and unstructured JSON data
- Mentored junior team members and often contributed tutorials and other documentation
- Delivered public- and client-facing thematic analysis of workplace collaboration messages
- Created labeling rule books, documented edge cases, and trained third party annotators

# Assistant Professor Data Science & Journalism University of Missouri 2017-2021

- Developed and taught courses on social media data, networks, machine learning, and statistics
- Mentored dozens of data science and journalism capstones and chaired two doctoral dissertations
- Developed and reviewed open-source data science tools, including popular bot detection software
- Served on various school and university committees related to data, education, and diversity

# Data ConsultantResearch Methods CenterUniversity of Kansas2016-2017

- Delivered feedback on interdisciplinary research projects across university system
- Led data science working groups on python, machine learning, and natural language processing
- Contributed to project automating personalized analytics for students in a large school district

#### Instructor Communication University of Kansas 2012-2016

- Created rtweet, a massively popular R package for collecting and analyzing Twitter data
- Instructor of record for quantitative methods, public speaking, leadership, and persuasion
- Updated and refined course materials for core quantitative research methods course

#### **Tools**

Languages
AWS Resources
Web Data Collection
Dev-Ops
Deep Learning
Machine Learning
Natural Language

Data Science
Data Visualization

Reporting

Python | R | SQL | Git | Docker | Bash | JavaScript
S3 | Sagemaker | ECR | Athena | Redshift | DynamoDB
REST/Stream APIs | requests | BS4 | HTTR | Rvest
Azure | Jira | GitHub | Gitlab | Confluence | Trello
PyTorch | TensorFlow | HuggingFace | Keras
Scikit-learn | XGBoost | FastText | Tidymodels
Spacy | HuggingFace | NLTK | RegEx | Scikit-learn
Polars | Pandas | Numpy | Tidyverse | Data.table
Ggplot2 | Ggvis | Plotly | Matplotlib | D3
JupyterNB | Markdown | Knitr | Quarto | LaTeX

#### **Skills**

Theory
Research Methods
Artificial Intelligence
Supervised Learning
Unsupervised Learning
Leadership

Communication | Media | Interpersonal | Opinion/Topic Mining
Experiments | Survey | Annotation | Algorithmic Labeling | Sampling
LLMs | Transformers | Human in the Loop | Reinforcement
Linear Models | Multilevel | Time Series | ANOVA | Structural Equation
Topic Modeling | Network Analysis | PCA | Factor Analysis | Similarity
Project Management | Team Supervisor | Committee Member & Chair

#### **Education**

| Ph.D. (with Honors)                             | University of Kansas      | Lawrence, KS    | 2017 |
|---|---------------------------|-----------------|------|
| Communication & Behavioral Sciences Methodology | /                         |                 |      |
| M.A. (with Honors)                              | University of Kansas      | Lawrence, KS    | 2014 |
| Communication Studies                           |                           |                 |      |
| B.S. (comprehensive)                            | Missouri State University | Springfield, MO | 2012 |
| Socio-Political Communication                   |                           |                 |      |

## **Publications (Selected)**

#### **Peer-Reviewed Articles**

- Comparative approaches to misinformation, International Journal of Communication, 2021
- Exploring gender differences on Twitter with NLP, Journal of Language and Social Psychology, 2021
- Collecting and analyzing Twitter data, Journal of Open-Source Software, 2019
- Analyzing change in network polarization, New Media Society, 2019
- Two tests of social displacement through social media use, Information, Communication, & Society, 2018
- Interpersonal goals and political uses of Facebook, Communication Research Reports, 2017

#### **Popular Press Articles**

- March Madness office talk on par with Vegas odds, PR Newswire, 2023
- Doubts cast over Elon Musk's Twitter bot claims, BBC News, 2022
- Using data science to uncover mystery author of Times' Op-ed, Reynolds Journalism Institute, 2018
- Trusting News project report, Trusting News, 2017

#### Open-Source Software

- tweetbotornot2: Detecting Twitter bots, 100,000 downloads / 27 citations, 2019
- textfeatures: Extracts features from text, 43,000 downloads / 4 citations, 2017
- rtweet: Collecting Twitter data, 1,100,000 downloads / 491 citations, 2016